Picture your dream living room.
想象一下你梦想中的客厅。
You're sitting on the sofa with the window open.
你坐在沙发上，窗户开着。
What do you hear?
你听到了什么？
Is it the sound of a flowing river?
是潺潺的流水声？
The murmuring of human chatter as friends enjoy a hot drink at the neighbouring cafe?
还是朋友们在邻近咖啡馆享用热饮时的低声交谈？
A soundscape is your aural environment – everything you can hear around you, and researchers say the soundscape where you live can influence your wellbeing.
声景就是你的听觉环境——你周围能听到的一切，研究人员表示，你所居住环境的声景会影响你的身心健康。
In times gone by, soundscapes would've consisted of the sounds of nature, such as birdcall and the sound of crashing waves.
在过去，声景通常由自然声音组成，比如鸟鸣和海浪拍打的声音。
The reality of human life in the 21st Century means that air travel, construction and traffic noises are now in the mix, and agricultural noise means that not even rural life is safe.
21世纪人类生活的现实意味着，航空旅行、建筑和交通噪音现在也混杂其中，而农业噪音意味着即使是乡村生活也不再安宁。
Noise pollution can lead to heightened stress levels, impaired cognitive function and higher risk of cardiovascular disease in humans, according to an article published by the UK Parliament called 'The effects of artificial light and noise on human health'.
根据英国议会发表的一篇题为《人造光和噪音对人类健康的影响》的文章，噪音污染会导致人类压力水平升高、认知功能受损以及心血管疾病风险增加。
Not only that, it can affect the behaviour and life cycles of species which rely on sound.
不仅如此，它还会影响依赖声音的物种的行为和生命周期。
So, what can be done?
那么，能做些什么呢？
Urban design is one trick.
城市规划是一种方法。
In Barcelona in Spain, urban planners designed 'superblocks', where traffic goes around big groups of buildings and the inner streets are pedestrianised, creating space for people and wildlife that is free from beeping horns and humming motors.
在西班牙巴塞罗那，城市规划者设计了"超级街区"，车流绕开大片的建筑群，内部街道被改为步行区，为人和野生动物创造了远离喇叭声和马达轰鸣声的空间。
In a 2025 article published in BMC Public Health, people in these areas reported an improvement in wellbeing, quality of sleep and reduction in noise.
在2025年发表在《BMC公共卫生》上的一篇文章中，这些地区的居民报告说，他们的健康状况、睡眠质量得到了改善，噪音也有所减少。
Other techniques include tree buffers, where trees are planted in urban areas to absorb sound energy.
其他方法包括树木缓冲带，即在城市地区种植树木以吸收声能。
In the Netherlands, they have created earth banks next to Schiphol airport to absorb noise from the runways and protect residents in the surrounding areas.
在荷兰，他们在史基浦机场旁边建造了土堤，以吸收跑道的噪音并保护周边地区的居民。
England has a vast network of hedgerows – they'd stretch around the Earth almost ten times if lined up!
英格兰拥有庞大的树篱网络——如果把它们排成一排，它们几乎可以绕地球十圈！
And it turns out they make excellent sound barriers, particularly if the hedges are large, dense and evergreen.
事实证明，它们是极好的隔音屏障，尤其是当树篱又大又密且四季常青时。
When we think about improving our environment, it's likely your mind jumps to reducing litter and air pollution.
当我们考虑改善环境时，你的脑海中很可能会想到减少垃圾和空气污染。
But reducing noise pollution is also important, to create a soundscape that works for everyone – people and wildlife.
但减少噪音污染也很重要，这样才能创造一个对所有人（人类和野生动物）都友好的声景。